Michelson, Vera. P.; Papers apap379
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Vera P. Michelson Papers
1921-2018
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap379
9.4 cubic ft.
This collection documents the lifelong activism of Albany, N.Y. resident Vera Michelson, especially her work with the Capital District Coalition Against Apartheid and Racism.
Content Description
This collection includes materials related to Vera Michelson's life and work as an activist and organizer in Albany, N.Y. and beyond. The collection documents her organization of the Capital District Coalition Against Apartheid and Racism (CD-CAAR) and work with the Social Justice Center; her national and international work against apartheid; her helping found ROOTS (Re-Entry Opportunities and Orientation Toward Success), a group established by ex-offenders and supporters to mentor the formerly incarcerated; her support of SNUG anti-gun violence; criminal justice reform; and her work with LEAD (Law Enforcement Assisted Diversion) in Albany. Most of the collection includes newspaper articles, correspondence, and meeting minutes related to Michelson's various social activism organizations. The Michelson collection also includes court documents relating to the court cases related to the Springbok Rugby protests in 1982. The collection consists of meeting minutes, notes, reports, clippings, subject files, audio, video, resource materials, posters, banners, and correspondence.
Biographical Note
Vera P. "Mike" Michelson (1945-2019) was a lifelong activist and organizer. Born in Northampton, Mass., she received her bachelor's degree from Russell Sage College and then a Master of Science degree in Education from the University at Albany.
Michelson was an employee of the State of New York for many years at the Oswald D. Heck developmental center. She retired in 2004, previously serving as president of her CSEA (Civil Service Employees Association) Local #445.
In 1981, Michelson helped organize the Capital District Coalition Against Apartheid and Racism (CD-CAAR) which opposed the U.S. tour of the South African Springboks rugby team, including its visit to Albany, N.Y. This led to even greater national and international anti-apartheid work and travel for Michelson who testified before the United Nations and traveled to an African National Congress Conference in Zambia. In Albany and the Capital District, Michelson was involved with many efforts involving social and racial justice. She led CD-CAAR's efforts to stop police brutality; was involved with efforts to reform the criminal justice system; worked to bring LEAD (Law Enforcement Assisted Diversion) to Albany; served as a volunteer administrator for Urban Grief, which supports families and communities traumatized by violence; helped to found ROOTS (Re-Entry Opportunities and Orientation Toward Success), a group established by ex-offenders and supporters to mentor the formerly incarcerated; and was involved with SNUG anti-gun violence initiatives.
Predeceased by her parents, she was survived by her brother and sister-in-law David and Carmen, her niece and nephews and their families.
Arrangement of the Collection
The Vera P. Michelson Papers are arranged in four series: Biography, Capital District Coalition against Apartheid and Racism (CD-CAAR), Social Activism, and Subject Files. Series 1 is arranged chronologically while Series 2-4 are arranged alphabetically.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
David Michelson, brother of Vera Michelson, donated all materials in this collection to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in June 2019 following Vera Michelson's death.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted with the exception of a small number of files noted at the folder level.
Related Materials
Please see apap011, the Capital District Coalition Against Apartheid and Racism Records, for materials related to Series 2 of the Michelson Papers. The majority of the Capital District Coalition Against Apartheid and Racism Records (Series 1-8) were lent to the Department of Special Collections by Vera Michelson in 1995 for microfilming. At Michelson's request, the materials were returned to her. Archivists believe many of these materials from 1995 were donated back to the Department in 2019 following Michelson's death in keeping with her wishes and are now part of Series 2 of the Michelson Papers.
Michelson, Vera P., 1945-2019; Capital District Coalition Against Apartheid and Racism; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Criminal Justice and Prisons; African Americans--New York (State)--Albany--Social Conditions; Violent crimes--New York (State)--Albany; Firearms and crime--New York (State)--Albany
- Biography, 1962-2018; Undated; 1; .7 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of information about Vera Michelson's personal life. This series contains newspaper articles, personal correspondence, and a copy of Michelson's birth certificate.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Debate League Tournament Papers, 1962; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificate of Birth Copy, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - C.E.O. Papers, 1969-1970; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Local #445 Union Papers (1 of 2), 1976-1979; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Local #445 Union Papers (2 of 2), 1976-1979; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - O.D. Heck Work Articles, 1976-1981; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Assorted Obituaries and Funeral Leaflets, 1976-2017; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Public Sector, 1979 February 7 (Flat-file 1)
  - Speeches, 1983; 1985; 2016; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - O.D. Heck Work Paper, 1985; 1995; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Awards and Commendations, 1985-2010; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence, "Lu", 1988 February 14 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Metroland Article about Vera Michelson and Apartheid, 1988 April 21/1988 April 27 (Flat-file 2)
  - Personal Politics, 2007; 2009-2010; 2017-2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Invitations and Event Programs, 2008; 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Car Accident Receipt, 2016 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - YWCA Award Announcement in Boston Post, Undated (Flat-file 3)
- Capital District Coalition Against Apartheid and Racism, 1967-1999; Undated; 2; 4.2 cubic ft.
  This series consists of records relating to Vera Michelson's involvement in the Capital District Coalition against Apartheid and Racism (CD-CAAR). The CD-CAAR series includes documents from various court cases involving Michelson, and other members of the CD-CAAR organization. The series also contains organizational pamphlets, correspondence, and newspaper articles related to the Springboks rugby controversy. There is a file on Malcomlm X's daughter Qubilah Shabazz's 1995 arrest for conspiring to kill Nation of Islam leader Louis Farrakhan containing information on the case, the FBI informant, and the informant's possible connections to Michelson and the Springbok protests 14 years earlier. In addition, the series includes organizational minutes, other correspondence, banners, and posters relating to its cultural boycott of apartheid. This series contains audio and video records as well as the paper records mentioned above.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - "Africa Called…Cuba Answered," U.S. Hands Off Cuba Event Post, Undated (Flat-file 4)
  - Amandla - the ANC Cultural Group, Undated (Cassette 1)
  - ANC National Conference Papers, 1992; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Angola A Vitoria e Certa. Recorded in Liberated Zones by Members of LS Movement Song of MPIA. Side B: Sung in Portuguese., 1970; Undated (Cassette 2)
  - Angolan Cultural Center - Cuba, V.M. (Cassette 3)
  - Anti-Apartheid in Sports Conference in Sweden, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anti-Apartheid in Sports Conference in Sweden, 1990 (Flat-file 5)
  - Anti-Apartheid, Pro-ANC Posters, Including Ones Condemning Ray Charles for Performing in South Africa, Undated (Flat-file 6)
  - Arrest Charges for People of NY v. Michelson, Estis and Young, 1981-1983; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Autographed "End Apartheid Vote for the People" Poster, Vote Democracy Campaign, Undated (Flat-file 7)
  - Barry/Clayton from SA, Undated (Cassette 4)
  - Bojana Jordan - the King, Undated (Cassette 5)
  - Cable #9, Marobe, Simpson, Michelson. Side B: Community Issues, 1985 March 25; 1985 October -05 (Cassette 6)
  - CASA Conference, 1987; 1989; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Capital District Conference on Crime and Criminal Justice, 1987-1996 (Flat-file 8)
  - Capital District Conference on Crime and Criminal Justice and Related Materials (1 of 2), 1987-1996; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Capital District Conference on Crime and Criminal Justice and Related Materials (2 of 2), 1987-1996; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - CD-CAAR 10 Year Anniversary (Video-tape 1)
  - CD-CAAR 10 Year Anniversary Materials, 1990-1991; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CD-CAAR 10th Anniversary, 1991 September 21 (Cd 1)
  - CD-CAAR Banner, Undated (Oversized 2)
  - CD-CAAR Red Banner, Undated (Oversized 1)
  - CD-CAAR Toast Presentation Materials, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cuba, Undated (Cassette 7)
  - Dakar, 1987 December (Cassette 8)
  - Fared Essack, Undated (Cassette 9)
  - Freedom Means, 1984 April 13 (Cassette 10)
  - Full Page Springboks' Rugby Game Retrospective, 1999 October 31 (Flat-file 9)
  - God Bless Africa, Nkosi Sikelel' iAfrika, Undated (Cassette 11)
  - Incomplete Court Documents, 1984; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Joe Slovo First Speech and Part of Second, 1990 October (Cassette 12)
  - Joe Slovo Third, Undated (Cassette 13)
  - Media, The Scene, 1988 (Flat-file 10)
  - Membership Lists, 2014; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Michelson and CD-CAAR v. Daly et al. 82-CV-1413 (1 of 2), 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Michelson and CD-CAAR v. Daly et al. 82-CV-1413 (2 of 2), 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Michelson and CD-CAAR v. Daly et al. 82-CV-1413 and Estis v. Daly et al. 82-CV-1412, 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Michelson and Estis v. Clyne et al., 1981; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Michelson et al. v. Daly et al. U.S. Court of Appeals, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Political (Video-tape 2)
  - Newsletters and Related Articles (1 of 2), 1987; 1990-1995; Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters and Related Articles (2 of 2), 1987; 1990-1995; Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper on Apartheid and South Africa Cultural Boycott, 1984 September/October (Flat-file 11)
  - Nhati, Mert and Me, 1990 February 25 (Cassette 14)
  - Oliver Tambo - Speech in Austria, 1987 (Cassette 15)
  - Organizational Articles and Fliers, 1992-1995; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Organizational Articles Fliers and Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Organizational Articles Fliers and Ephemera, 1981-1984; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Organizational Articles, Notes, and Ephemera, 1985-1987; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Organizational Correspondence (1 of 2), 1982-1989; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Organizational Correspondence (2 of 2), 1982-1989; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Organizational Correspondence, 1990-1994; Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - People of NY v. Young and Spearman (1 of 4), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - People of NY v. Young and Spearman (2 of 4), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - People of NY v. Young and Spearman (3 of 4), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - People of NY v. Young and Spearman (4 of 4), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - President O.R. Tambo ANC Closing Speech at Austria, Undated (Cassette 16)
  - Qubilah Shabazz, 1995; Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Qubilah Shabazz, 1995; Undated (Flat-file 13)
  - Ray Charles Protest, 1985-1989; Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Research Pamphlets, 1977; 1983; 1986; Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rio School - High School, Undated (Cassette 17)
  - SCAAR BK and Lat Student Lead, 1992 April 5 (Cassette 18)
  - SCAN/Mandela WCDB, 1988 May (Cassette 19)
  - SOMAFCO (Cassette 20)
  - SOMAFCO (Cassette 21)
  - SOMAFCO #3 and #4, Undated (Cassette 22)
  - Soviet Rep, Mozambique Rep, Undated (Cassette 23)
  - Springbok Albany Visit, Local News Coverage, 1981 (Cd 2)
  - Springbok Rugby Controversy Corning/Empire State Plaza, 1981 (Cd 3)
  - Springbok Rugby Footage in Albany NY, 1981 (Video-tape 3)
  - Springboks Rugby Game Court Case(s) Correspondence, 1982; Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Springboks Rugby Game Police Surveillance Records and Albany Police Arrest Paperwork Related to Young, Spearman, Michelson, and Estis, 1981-1982; Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Springboks Rugby Game Protest Articles (1 of 2), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Springboks Rugby Game Protest Articles (2 of 2), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Springboks Rugby Game Protest Articles and Ephemera, 1981-1982; Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Springboks Rugby Game Protest Retrospective Publications, Including John Warren Study, 1988-2014; Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - South Africa Cultural Boycott Apologies, 1983-1987; Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - South Africa Cultural Boycott Articles-Local, 1982-1988; Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - South Africa Cultural Boycott-Chick Corea Protest, 1983-1985; Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - South Africa Cultural Boycott National Articles, 1967-1985; Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - South Africa Cultural Boycott National Articles, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - SWAPO and ANC Banner, Undated (Oversized 2)
  - Testimony Before U.N. General Assembly, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - U.N. Lists of Cultural Boycott Entertainers, 1982-1984; 1986; 1988; Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - U.N. Special Committee AG. Apartheid Honours Stevie Wonder, New York, 1985 May 13 (Cassette 24)
  - Vera Michelson v. City of Albany, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Vera Michelson FOIA Requests - RESTRICTED, 1982-1984; Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Must consult an archivist before viewing.
  - Viva Angola Libre Banner, Undated (Oversized 1)
  - WBAI Interview, Undated (Cassette 25)
  - WGY, 1991 September 21 (Cassette 26)
  - WGY, 1991 September 23 (Cassette 27)
  - WGY Interview with Mike re: Rugby Lawsuit, 1988 (Cassette 28)
  - Women and Children Under Apartheid, Wilborn Temple, 1987 June 12 (Cassette 29)
  - Zaire, 1985; 1987-1988; 1991; 1993 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Social Activism, 1982-2018; Undated; 3; 3.0 cubic ft.
  The social activism series includes information regarding Vera Michelson's activism with organizations outside of the Capital District Coalition against Apartheid and Racism. This series includes records relating to Cure Violence, SNUG, Urban Grief, and ROOTS (Re-Entry Opportunities and Orientation Toward Success). Michelson devoted her life to these social activism organizations, which often intersected in their missions to address racial discrimination and gun violence in the Capital District. This series includes meeting minutes, correspondence, newspaper articles, and ephemera from the various organizations.
  Arraned alphabetically.
  - African American Family Day, 1982; 1985; 1986; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Albany City Charter Revision, 2005-2006; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Albany Police Officers Union and Mesley, Christian, 2009-2010; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alice, 1996 December 12 (Cassette 30)
  - Anne Pope, Tom Keefe, 1996 November 11 (Cassette 31)
  - Bill Ritchie, 1996 September 26 (Cassette 32)
  - Burning Flames, Me, NA, Fraid, Undated (Cassette 33)
  - "Call To Action" Meeting, 1995; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Capital District Prog. Radio, "Mike", WRPI, 1996 August 22 (Cassette 34)
  - Capital District Progressive Radio, March 19th Coalition, 1996 April 11 (Cassette 35)
  - Capital District Progressive Radio, Morris, 1996 September 12 (Cassette 36)
  - Care-a-Van, Vera Michelson, 1988 May 29 (Cassette 37)
  - Ceasefire Subject Files, 2008-2013; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Coalition for Accountable Police and Government, 2004; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Coalition - "Stop Racist Violence Forum", 1988 April 23 (Cassette 38)
  - Coalition - "Stop Racist Violence Forum" - Roger Green, 1988 April 23 (Cassette 39)
  - Community Cookout for Catwan Hawkins, 2016 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CORE, 2006; 2013-2016; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cure Violence Advisory Panel Information, 2015; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cure Violence-Canvassing Resources, 2014; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cure Violence Job Interviews and Applications - RESTRICTED, 2014-2017; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cure Violence Meeting Minutes and Correspondence, 2014; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cure Violence Organizational Ephemera, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cure Violence-Peace March, 2017; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cure Violence-Personal Notes, 2017-2018; Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cure Violence-Subject Files and Notices, 2013-2016; Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Domestic Violence - WRPI, Undated (Cassette 40)
  - Inside to Outside, Undated (Cassette 41)
  - Inside to Outside on 1201, 1997 March 27 (Cassette 42)
  - "Justice in the Making" Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Justice in the Making" Personal Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Justice in the Making" Subject Files, 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - LEAD Meeting Minutes and Correspondence (1 of 2), 2016-2018; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - LEAD Meeting Minutes and Correspondence (2 of 2), 2016-2018; Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - LEAD Organizational Ephemera, 2015-2018; Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - LEAD Personal Notes, 2016-2017; Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - LEAD Subject Files, 2011; 2013-2018; Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Locking Them Down: From Inside to Outside - David White and David Howard - WRPI Prog #4, 1997 March 27 (Cassette 43)
  - Locking Them Down: Mentally Ill - WRPI Radio, 1997 February 27 (Cassette 44)
  - Locking Them Down: Monroe Parrot, Randy Meese, 1996 December 5 (Cassette 45)
  - Locking Them Down: Wright, McGrath, Lynch, part 6, 1997 April 24 (Cassette 46)
  - Locking Them Down: WRPI - Jim Acker, Randy Moore, Capital Punishment, 1997 April 10 (Cassette 47)
  - Locking Them Down: Youth, Some College, Some Jail, 1997 February 13 (Cassette 48)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. "Organizing" Banner, 1991 (Oversized 2)
  - Minority Forum, Interview Mike/Clayn, 1993 April 9 (Cassette 49)
  - Minority Forum, Black and Jew, Side 1, 1994 May 26 (Cassette 50)
  - Minority Forum, Simpson Rosenblum, Side 2, 1994 May 26 (Cassette 51)
  - Mozambique Solidarity Office, Prexy Nesbitt, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - NESASN Campaigns, 1989; Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - NESASN Correspondence, 1988-1990; Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - NESASN Funding, 1986; 1989; Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - NESASN Mailing List, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - NESASN Minutes, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Panel, Racist Violence, Tape #2, Undated (Cassette 52)
  - Promo AESPP, Undated (Cassette 53)
  - Re-election Bid for Kathy Sheehan (1 of 2), 2016-2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Re-election Bid for Kathy Sheehan (2 of 2), 2016-2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - ROOTS Affiliated Agencies (1 of 2), 2007-2015; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - ROOTS Affiliated Agencies (2 of 2), 2007-2015; Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - ROOTS Altamont Re-entry Task Force, 2010-2013; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - ROOTS Correspondence and Meeting Minutes (1 of 3), 1997-1999; 2007-2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - ROOTS Correspondence and Meeting Minutes (2 of 3), 1997-1999; 2007-2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - ROOTS Correspondence and Meeting Minutes (3 of 3), 1997-1999; 2007-2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - ROOTS Job Fair, 2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - ROOTS Organizational Ephemera, 1998-2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - ROOTS Personal Notes (1 of 2), 2012-2016; Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - ROOTS Personal Notes (2 of 2), 2012-2016; Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - ROOTS Research Subject Files, 2008; 2010-2011; Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - SNUG Albany Violence Subject Files (1 of 2), 2012-2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - SNUG Albany Violence Subject Files (2 of 2), 2012-2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - SNUG Correspondence and Meeting Minutes, 2008; 2011-2014; 2018; Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - SNUG Organizational Papers and Ephemera, 2008; Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - SNUG Shootings and Stabbings, 2010-2013 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Tough on Crime, Alice Green, etc., 1997 March 12 (Cassette 54)
  - TRAC Mentoring - RESTRICTED, 2013; 2015; Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Trauma Response Team Correspondence and Pamphlets, 2001-2011; Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Trauma Response Team Personal Notes, 2011-2014; 2017; Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Unite for Prison and Parole Justice" Advocacy Day, 2016-2017; Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Urban Grief Correspondence and Meeting Minutes (1 of 2), 2015-2018; Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Urban Grief Correspondence and Meeting Minutes (2 of 2), 2015-2018; Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Urban Grief Personal Notes, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - WBAI, Vera on WBAI in NYC "Emanations," Mike and Haitians, 1994 June 26 (Cassette 55)
  - Williams, Ellazar Case, 2018; Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - WRPI, Undated (Cassette 56)
  - WRPI - Me, Undated (Cassette 57)
  - WRPI Prog. Radio, 1996 August 22 (Cassette 58)
  - WRPI Protest Music, 1997 January 15 (Cassette 59)
  - WRPI - Sentenced to Death - Jim Acker, 1997 April 10 (Cassette 60)
  - Youth Empowerment Movement-1st Youth Black History Month, 2012 February 4 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Subject Files, 1921-2018; Undated; 4; 1.5 cubic ft.
  Vera Michelson collected and maintained subject files relating to various groups and people relating to her criminal justice reform efforts and community activism. This series includes records Michelson collected about different figures in the Albany area, including friends she made through her activism. The series also has records used by Michelson for research into some of her social activism organizations. This series is comprised of mostly newspaper articles and organizational ephemera like pamphlets and business cards.
  - Albany Fire Department Diversity Efforts, 2006; 2011; 2015-2018; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Albany Immigrant Detention Center, 2017-2018 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Albany Police Department Chief Searches, 2000; 2002; 2010; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Albany Police Department Racial Equity Training, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Albany Politics, 2004-2005; 2007; 2010-2014; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Albany Violence, 1999-2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Albany Violence Personal Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anthony Robbins/Norman Cousins, Undated (Cassette 61)
  - Articles Related to Various Friends -RESTRICTED, 1972-1986; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Assorted Business Cards, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Burgess, Brother Yusuf Papers - RESTRICTED, 2011; 2013-2015; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Criminal Justice Reform (1 of 2), 2013; 2015-2018; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Criminal Justice Reform (2 of 2), 2013; 2015-2018; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - CSDA MWBE/Workforce Development Community Workshop, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Domestic Violence and Incarceration, 1996-1997; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Drug Related Arrests, 2012-2013; 2018 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - GIVE, 2015; Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Government Surveillance, 1978; 1982-1983; 1987-1988; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Green, Alice in The Times Union, 1993 April 4 (Flat-file 14)
  - Housing Resources, 2005-2006; Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - How to Put on a Minstrel Show Booklet, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Hurley, Jackie, 1976; Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Islam #6 Tape 1: Malcolm X, Islam and Black Liberation, Undated (Cassette 62)
  - Islam #6 Tape 2: Malcolm X, Islam and Black Liberation, Undated (Cassette 63)